Kassoy, Bernard Teachers Union Cartoons 6107 G
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Bernard Kassoy Teachers Union Cartoons
1900-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Kassoy, Bernard
6107 G
0.61 cubic feet
0.6 linear ft.
Cartoons.
134 original cartoons and 6 posters
5798895
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 14, 2013
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, September 14, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Bernard Kassoy's art has ranged over many media during the past half-century, and his relentless imagination still continues to explore new forms, themes and methods. He has worked professionally in oil, watercolor, gouache, pastel, charcoal, and pencil, and he has done etching, engraving, lithography, intaglio, woodcuts and monotypes. He has carved stone and cast in bronze, done portraits and landscapes, editorial cartoons and abstractions, stage design, book illustration and photography.
Scope and Contents
Drawings depicting issues facing teachers and teachers' unions including anti-Communist struggles, and issues of employment, pay, facilities, and government aid to schools.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Kassoy, Bernard, 1914-; American Federation of Teachers. Local 5 (New York, N.Y.)
5798895
- Kassoy Portraits (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Above a quote from a New York Post editorial that The danger is not that our schools are subversive, but that they are senile, and amidst the shattered school buildings, the Board of Education continues its hunt for reds in schools., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  February 27, 1960.
- Toward Higher Horizons, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  October 10, 1959. Man walks up steps titled Parent Cooperation, Guidance, Remedial Help and Enriched School Programs. Against the background of the optimistic statement of Superintendent of schools John J. Theobald that "we are aping resources of unbelievable riches that have been all along neglected," a student moves up the steps of an enriched school program, remedial help, guidance and parent cooperation "toward higher horizons."
- Still Out of Reach, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  January 14, 1961. Retired teacher climbs ladder after her "Adequate Pension" which has sprouted wings and is flying away.
- Consumer Prices at Record High, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  March 29, 1958. Man climbs a short set of crumbling steps, following the cost of living on a chart behind him, however, the cost of living continues to rise, and the man can go no farther up
- Businessman falls from clouds labeled Professional Salary Level while reading the headline, Report Teacher Pay Raised (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Top education Brass smile over their Prosperity budget, while teachers kicked to the ground by large shoe, representing their Austerity budget (Box 2, Folder 6)
- The Breaking Point, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  January 28, 1950. Teacher is stretched with rope by man in glasses, the lengths teacher is stretched are marked by the demands on their time, 25+ period weeks, 30+ period weeks and extra curricular activities, while the school official, wielding the stretching device, asks, "What stretchout?"
- How Did That Happen?, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  September 26, 1959. Massive Board of Education member sits on top of overcrowded school while reading the headline "900 Teaching Positions Dropped in Reallocation of Funds"
- No Help to Morale, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  February 05, 1955. Substitute teacher looks at menacing stack on her desk, reading "Board of Education to resist decision granting sick pay to subs", "No Tenure", "No Pension", "Layoffs"
- Man happily hugs bag of $40-50 million of found city funds while child pickets for teachers with a placard reading Better Salaries! Smaller Classes! Improved School Conditions!, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  November 05, 1960.
- Teachers leap off cliff reaching for an apple which reads, Merit Pay and fall through the words, Low Pay for All, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  October 01, 1960.
- Needed: A Giant Step, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  February 23, 1957. Man walks over "Heald Report" bridge, however is not able to reach the other side, labeled "School Needs." News item: "They turned out to be 'baby steps' at a time when 'giant steps' are needed," said Board of Education President Charles H. Silver at the hearing on the Governor's budget. He was referring to the 1956 Heald Commission recommendation on State education budget increases." The cartoon graphically illustrated the Commission's baby steps toward the meeting of the school needs when giant steps are needed.
- Large man in tuxedo sits at desk, listening to man in cap and gown, with a chart showing a growing war production index pointing to hot war (Box 2, Folder 13)
- And Make Sure We Get It, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  January 21, 1950. A large bag of money sings "Happy New Year" to Mr. Big, a top city official, while Miss Teacher reaches out to a fleeing two cents who say, "Maybe next July, maybe!"
- The Man who came to Dinner, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  December 15, 1951. Monstrous man wearing a shirt reading, "Inflation" is eating a giant meal as two normal sized people eat meagerly
- Dont Let it Break, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  May 27, 1961. "Federal Aid" Two unnamed forces- possibly city and state governments- play tug of war, with the rope representing education, and may, by their efforts, sever the lifeline to the schools.
- Wage Frozen; Prices?, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  March 10, 1951. "Deep Freeze 1951 Model" Wages frozen in the bottom of large block of ice, while prices stand on tip-toes on top of the cube
- Uncle Sam sits atop sign, Shortage of Science Teachers continues while watching the Soviet satellite Sputnik circling in outer space., 1957 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  November 02, 1957.
- 50 million added to the State Nest Egg:, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  March 18, 1961. the New York Times reported earlier that month- which is captured well by the cartoon showing the governor sitting on the "State Fund" nest egg, while the New York City schoolchildren look on forlornly.
- Timeo Danaos [et] Dona Ferentes (I Fear the Greeks bearing Gifts), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  November 15, 1958. Using the classical Trojan Horse of "superior merit" to cloak its misdeeds, a figure probably representing the Board of Education and bearing the shield with "no pay increases" emerges, thereby justifying the use of the words of caution in the title.
- A hand reaches for help from the water from a boat, the hand is labeled All the Schools and the boat, labeled Massive Federal Aid (Box 2, Folder 21)
- In box 1, three candidates are at a podium on the verge of giving their pledge on the matter of salary increases. In box 2, they have fled (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Reminder, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  March 22, 1958. Teacher leans over sign reading "Salary Increase and Smaller Classes Now!" while the Mayor sits in his "Budget Retreat"
- A man fighting for Night Staff Unity slays the dragon that is Low Salaries, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  March 07, 1959.
- Education in 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  January 09, 1960. A large question mark looms in the distance as Uncle Sam and the New Year baby look on
- Classroom Intruder, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  November 24, 1951. A giant with money in his pockets and a shirt reading "War Hysteria" shows a teacher his lesson plan. The dilemma faced by the teacher trying to do his job while the thought-control agents of war hysteria examine his lesson plan for possible signs of disloyalty (read "free expression")
- They Uphold Your Rights, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  January 13, 1951. The 8 victims of persecution for their political beliefs are shown here as stemming the tide of repression and protecting the Bill of Rights for all of us. Repression, as a giant mass of water, looks to break down the Bill of Rights, which is supported by an arm whose sleeve reads, "The 8"
- Not the Teachers Union Way, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  April 07, 1951. A gangster and a politician stand back to back. The gangster hands the politician money as the politician is saying "Not me" into a microphone.
- A finger flips the voting lever under the choice Save our Schools (Box 2, Folder 29)
- In Protective Custody, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  October 06, 1951. A police officer stands over the tattered remains of the Bill of Rights while the Constitution looks on from its cell
- A cap and gown, with a dollar sign, $, for a face stands under the quote, Reds, pinks, and near-pinks cant teach here. They dont have to come here if they dont want to. Thats my definition of academic freedom., 1900 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  Quote from President F. Schweitzer, Bloomfield College, NJ.
- Its Later than you Think, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  March 25, 1950. A "reactionary 'vet'" in full uniform, representing mainly the American Legion, with money symbols on his patches, puts his arm around a bigot's shoulder, while the bigot sharpens his witch-hunting blade.
- Achieve Unity by September!, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  June 23, 1951. A thumb-down hand reads, "United Teacher Organizations" while a man wearing a shirt reading "Threats, Coercion" pickets for more work and no pay. This is a dramatic call for united action by the different teacher organizations to achieve unity for their common goals by September against the enemies of education using threats and coercion to degrade the wages and condition of teachers.
- Quiet! Board at Work, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  September 11, 1954. A man looks through a microscope at a dot on his desk, "RED" written next to it, while on a blackboard behind him, in big letters is written, "Overcrowding, low salaries, dilapidated buildings, inadequate supplies, delinquency, worn-out texts, reading defects, delayed entrance age.". While all these problems remain unattended to, the Board of Education is shown concentrating on the discovery of a "red."
- A teacher tells a child before he can enroll in school, he must promise he is not a member of the Communist Party (Box 2, Folder 35)
- A hand of bones signs the name, Harvey Dexter White Lawrence Duggan Minnie Lutride (Box 2, Folder 36)
- A dog named Yellow Press barks Reds! Reds! Reds! at the names Einstein, Thomas Mann, Hutchins, MeikleJohn, O. John Rogge, Harlow Shapley, Jon De Boer. (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Stepping Stone, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  May 22, 1954. A man puts the "Expert Witch Hunt Award" on the President of the Board of Education's chair. Just as Trial Examiner Arthur Levitt used his recommendation for the dismissal of highly qualified teachers as a stepping stone to a judgeship and beyond [see above], so the recipient of the "Expert Witch Hunt Award" uses that dubious honor to propel him into the position of president of the Board of Education."
- Now unmask the School McCarthys, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  December 11, 1954. A man wearing a t-shirt logo reading "School Witch Hunts" throws off a facemask. Same man depicted in the bottom center with scarf around face. Caption in center reads "Senate Censure." In 1954, following his disastrous performance in the Army-McCarthy hearings, the United States Senate passed a resolution of censure against the senator. Here, the cartoonist is calling for similar action against the perpetrators of the witch hunts against New York City's teachers.
- Man squatting with pencil in hand, looking through a door keyhole and another man standing on his back with pencil in hand and notebook in his pocket looking through the window over the door. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  The partial sign on the door reads "Room 46." A book lays open on the ground reading "Witch Hunt Book".
- A hand, labeled justice, is holding scales. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  On the left hand side the blocks are named "Scholarship", "Character", "Superior teaching records" and "Parent pleas". On the right hand side of the scale there is a block named "20 year old application", and a finger labeled "Refusal to inform" is pressing down on top of it.
- or were you ever?, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  October 13, 1951. In the bottom right hand corner a man with the title "Superintendent of Witch Hunts" is consulting a "list of subversives to be questioned" and looking up at three men labeled, "Washington: Leader of the American Revolution", Jefferson: the Declaration of Independence", and Lincoln: the Gettysburg Address". This title is part of the mantra of the investigating committees: "Are you now or were you ever a member of the Communist Party?"
- A large thumb labeled Reaction is pressing down on a body labeled Federal Aid. (Box 2, Folder 43)
- A building labeled Free Public Colleges with a bar labeled Tuition, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  December 03, 1960. Fees" is fastened by a padlock. There is a man standing on the steps staring at the lock and a dejected looking girl walking away from the building.
- For Brotherhood Week: A Tree that must not grow in Brooklyn, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  February 18, 1950. The tree of bigotry is topped by the figure of May Quinn, a Brooklyn teacher who was accused of spreading the poison of anti-Semitism and other forms of bigotry in her classroom. In 1942, Ms. Quinn used a vicious anti-Semitic leaflet as the basis for a discussion in her civics class. Teachers at her school also claimed that she had said all Communists were Jews and that Italians were "greasy foreigners." Unlike the haste with which the Board of Education was later to act against teachers with exemplary records accused of being "Communists," it took three years of concerted pressure by teachers, parents and civic organizations before charges were preferred against Ms. Quinn. Among her supporters was Father Edward Lodge Curran, eastern representative of Father Charles E. Coughlin's notoriously anti-Semitic publication, Social Justice. The Board acquitted her of most of the charges, found her guilty only of neglect of duty and poor judgment and fined her two weeks' pay. In 1949, when Ms. Quinn made racist statements during a current events lesson, Superintendent of Schools William Jansen, who presided over the witch-hunt that was later to strip the schools of its finest teachers, reported that he had informed Ms. Quinn of his "keen dissatisfaction" and "contemplated no further action."
- After-School Work-Load, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  December 19, 1959. A man is carrying a load of papers on his back, labeled "After-School Work-Load". Individual packets are labeled "Marketing papers", "Help to Individual Pupils", "Preparations", "Department Meetings", "Faculty Meetings", "Special Programs & Events", "Publications". "Dramatics by Class", and "Parent Conferences." In the top left hand corner there are two signs reading P.S. 91 and 3p.m. School's Out!
- A man playing a violin is sitting on top of a burning building. Some of the flames are labeled Out-of License Teachers, Subs Leaving, and "Temporary, Fill-in Subs., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  October 08, 1960. A school official, quoted in the World Telegram and Sun as saying that "All in all, our schools are in pretty good shape staff wise this fall," is shown "fiddling" while Rome burns in the form of out-of-license teachers and substitutes leaving the system being replaced by temporary, fill-in substitutes.
- Mired Down, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  May 31, 1958. Man stands up to ankles in water with words such as "Segregation", "Overburdened, Underpaid Teachers", "Poor Equipment" etc A delinquent student is shown mired in the swamp of violence in films, TV and comics, no recreational facilities, overcrowded classes, poor equipment, overburdened, underpaid teachers, underprivileged neighborhoods and the evils of segregation.
- Peter and the Dyke. A Modern Fairy Tale, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  March 01, 1958. Water labeled "Real School Needs" bursts over the top of a dam on which a member of the Board of Education is writing, "More '600' Schools."
- Dont Lower Your Banner, Mr. Mayor, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  March 27, 1954. Newly elected New York City Mayor Robert F. Wagner is urged by teachers not to abandon his campaign pledges to meet the teachers' salary demands.
- In first box, politician gives thumbs up to sign reading, Pay Raises for Teachers!, then in second box after election, twiddles his thumbs next to sign declaring, No Raises for Teachers (Box 2, Folder 51)
- A man with a Feinberg Subversion Detector on his back, takes a measurement over a students shoulder (Box 2, Folder 52)
- A line of inspectors and examiners size one another up, each looking over the others shoulder finally examining a one person. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  In charge of the inspection is a large hand with a magnifying glass and a swastika on his wrist.
- An Impartial Trial Examiner holding Levitt Reports runs up steps labeled Witch Hunt Teacher Firings towards a star reading, Judgeship (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Man in suit and spectacles offers teachers choice between six and a half dozen, however on the matter of increasing the teaching load to 30 periods for special subjects, he offers the teachers orders (Box 2, Folder 55)
- At Parents Night, Principal tells parents how their children are taught freedoms of speech and press in the school, however, during school, the same principal is shown censoring the student press (Box 2, Folder 56)
- A man in a graduation cap and a tie stands naked in a barrel reading, The Dignity of the Profession while floating in clouds labeled cost of living, rent rises, price rises and inflation (Box 2, Folder 57)
- No Coercion?, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  June 16, 1951. The Board of Education bureaucrat, armed with the weapon of a charge of insubordination, offers the teacher the opportunity to "volunteer" for extracurricular activities.
- A Happy Summer to All, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  June 26, 1954. A teacher shuts his "unfinished" file drawer on topics such as, "New School Building" "pensions", "pay raise" etc
- The Unequal Match, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  September 08, 1951. A large boxer with the words "Tax increases" and "Continuing Price Rises" written on his chest dwarfs much smaller boxer on whom a tag from his shorts is labeled, "Piddling Raise for Teachers."
- How to Solve Problems, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  February 25, 1950. A Board of Education official tries to close a trunk containing the evils of old buildings, overcrowded schools, teacher shortages, and "25-5 For All" while flaunting the solution of crying "Red! Red! Red!" He points at a fish skeleton around which the word "RED!" is written three times
- Back-Breaking Load, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  May 26, 1951. A man representing Teacher morale, carries an extremely large man carrying a briefcase labeled, "Extra-Curricular Activities Decision." The uncompensated extracurricular activities that Education officials seek to foist on teachers are depicted here as combined with inadequate pay, overcrowded classes, dilapidated buildings, the Timone Resolution and its concomitant witch hunts and repression to produce sinking teacher morale.
- Two hobos read are prompted to read a casting call for a new production called The Informer Looking for top stoolpigeon roles, sin-singers, canaries., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  September 25, 1954. While the Board of Education casts its net for informers who will at stool pigeons and lackeys, two unemployed passers-by turn thumbs down with the statement, "Not for us pal, we have our pride."
- A woman in a crown with a necklace dangling money explains why teachers must be laid off and then new teachers rehired each year (Box 2, Folder 64)
- Ideal Teacher (Box 2, Folder 65)
  A man's mouth is tied up, his ears blocked and opaque sunglasses cover his eyes
- A mouse with a gavel announces from his hole, The motion is passed No comment, please Meeting adjourned! A moment later, a foot reading, Public Protest shoos the mouse back in his hole (Box 2, Folder 66)
- 1949: Campaign Sellout Robot politician promises raises for teachers; 1950: Campaign Sellout Robot politician promises raises for teachers; 1951: Large man wearing United Teachers across his back cowers over politician (Box 2, Folder 67)
- Man on horseback, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  February 03, 1951. Governor Thomas E. Dewey on a horse brandishes flag, "'Emergency' Powers Proposal" His horse has a sash reading, "War War War" and his sword reads, "Schools last!"
- Without the Clancy bill benefits, man goes from genteel poverty before retirement to destitution afterwards; with the Clancy bill benefits, this trend is reversed, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  1962?.
- A Final Push Needed, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  March 05, 1960. "More State Aid!" Three monstrous fingers point at Governor, demanding aid. Teachers are urged to pressure Governor Rockefeller for more state aid.
- A man and woman, representing the united teaching staff and its various organizations, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  January 28, 1961. Heading by train as a delegation to Albany, scheduled for two weeks thereafter, of lobby for increased state aid, a professional salary raise (as opposed to the "piddling" raises previously offered) and pension improvements.
- The state and city split plate of surplus budget, while child looks on through the window (Box 2, Folder 72)
- Needed: A Clean Sweep, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  September 14, 1961. Broom labeled, "New Board of Education", sweeps away papers reading, "Low staff salaries", "overcrowded classes", "poor supplies" etc
- Governor Rockefellers Roadblock, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  February 20, 1960. Two students follow a sign "To Better Schools" however, reach a dead end, on the wall is written, "'Pay-As-You-Go' School Financing Proposal"
- A loaf of bread is labeled $50,000,000 of Teacher Salary Raises. First, the Board of Education takes a slice, second the Mayor takes a slice, then when the day comes, what will be left for the teachers?, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  April 02, 1960.
- A man representing Federal, State, Sales and Excise taxes reaches through a teachers window and says, Dont bother with the forms, just HAND IT OVER! (Box 2, Folder 76)
- Unkindest cut of all, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  October 15, 1960. An axe labeled budget cuts splits two buildings, the building on the right "building proposal" and the building on the left, "new school"
- Take a Giant Step, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  February 20, 1954. A man steps from NYC to Albany with a paper in his hand reading "40,000 United Teachers"
- Another Proud Achievement, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  October 08, 1955. The printer is holding the latest achievement of the Teacher's Union's Teacher News publication: An Italian-American Supplement to add to the special issues for Negro History Week and the Jewish Tercentenary, in addition to the Puerto Rican Day Supplement, the Primer for New Teachers and the Pension Primer.
- Strengthening Democracy, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  February 11, 1950. Board of Education official holds rifle in hand and points to signature line underneath the words "I hereby volunteer-"
- Time for a New Suit, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  January 07, 1961. A teacher stands before the 1961 Budget Planners wearing a coat held together with "A lick," "A promise," Patch-work Raise, 1957" etc
- Baseball scoreboard announces major successes for Teacher Union, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 82)